嘿，你们好，我是TheCherno，欢迎回到我的游戏引擎系列
hey, what's up guys, my name is TheCherno, welcome back to my game engine series
那么上期我们终于用着色器正确地绘制了一个三角形，那应该对每个人都有用
so the last time we finally actually used shaders to draw a triangle properly, and that should work for everyone
今天我们要讲一些我们还没讲过的东西
today we're going to talk about something that we haven't talked about
到目前为止，我们只是想尽快把所有内容显示在屏幕上
thus far we kind of just wanted to get everything up onto the screen as quickly as possible
在我们的Application类中，对吧，只有一些原始的OpenGL代码
just having kind of raw OpenGL code, right, inside our application class
并且今天我们终于要讨论些渲染接口的设计和抽象了
and today we're finally getting to discussing kind of the design the abstraction of these kind of renderer api course
我们有的OpenGL那些接口，以及我们如何处理多个渲染接口
that we have currently with OpenGL, and how we're actually going to handle multiple renderer apis
因为那是个非常重要的问题，当你们在考虑游戏引擎时，那确实需要处理
because that's a pretty big issue, that really needs to be addressed, when you're thinking about game engine the line
特别是如果你们想有某种支持多种接口的渲染引擎
especially if you want to actually have some kind of renderer engine that supports multiple apis
在游戏引擎中，这是种很重要的抽象，通常与多平台有关
it's kind of too big kind of abstractions that go on in game engines, usually to do with kind of multiple platforms
那是多个实际的平台，像Windows Mac Linux Android iOS PS for Xbox switch等等
and that is the multiple actual platforms, right,so stuff like Windows Mac Linux Android iOS, PS for Xbox switch whatever
那些就是你们实际处理不同平台的抽象，还有渲染器接口抽象
those kind of abstractions where you're actually dealing with different platforms, and there's also the renderer api abstraction
你们在处理渲染器接口的潜力，它实际上就是支持多个渲染接口
in which you're dealing with the potential for renderer apis, that it actually basically supporting multiple rendering apis
所以能够使用DirectX渲染，OpenGL，Vulcan之类的接口，所以这两个都是非常大的主题
so being able to render using DirectX, using OpenGL, using Vulcan, any of that kind of stuff, so both are very big discussions
很明显，我们今天讨论了渲染器接口，我也想看看关于这个有很多学派的思想
obviously we got talking about renderer apis today, and I also want to kind of see that there's lot of schools of thought on this
在我的职业生涯中，见过很多和我喜欢的方式不同的来实现这个的方法
I've seen in my professional career, I've seen a lot of different ways of doing this the way that I like doing it
我们要为Hazel实现这个的方法只是众多方法中的一种，不像没有正确的方法
and the way that we're going to do it for Hazel is just one of the many ways, don't like there's no correct way
这取决于哪种方法适合你们的需求，比如实际上喜欢什么，以及你们希望接口是什么样
it depends on what kind of suits your needs, and what you actually like, and what you want the api to look like
并且你们想让代码看起来像编程，撸码是一件很主观的事情
and what you want the code to look like programming, and just you know, writing code is such a subjective kind of thing
我的意思是，是的，有客观事实可以确定这样做，但从技术理论上来说，可能就比较糟糕
I mean yes, there are objective truths as to sure you could do it this way, but it's like technically on paper worse in every way
当然，代码可能看起来很漂亮，但性能很差，抽象很差，接口很糟糕
like sure the code might look pretty, but the performance is bad, the abstraction is bad, the api is terrible
我想如果代码很不错，接口不会太糟糕，但你们明白我的意思
well I guess if the code is pretty, the api wouldn't be terrible, but you get my drift
我非常相信做正确的事情，是的，代码可能更难读，它可能不那么好
I'm a big believer of doing things like properly in a sense of, yes, the code might be harder to read, and it might not be as nice
但它的运行速度会更快，显然我有EA游戏引擎工程的背景
but it's gonna perform faster, obviously me coming from a background of like game engine engineering at EA
我们当然关心性能，因为我们试图突破极限，所以考虑那点很重要
we definitely care about performance, because we're trying to push the limits, so it's important to kind of consider that
那就是我作为一个程序员的本能，我真的很在乎性能，我喜欢那样做
and that's kind of just, that's kind of just who I am as a programmer, I really care about performance, and I like to kind of do it that way
不管怎样，永远不会满足于那个，我想对所有支持这个系列的朋友表示衷心的感谢
anyway, I don't wanna blab her on forever, I wanna give a huge thank you to all the patrons that made the series possible
如果你们访问patreon.com/thecherno支持，就能提前看到视频
patreon.com/thecherno, if you guys sign up there, you'll get videos early
你们就可以访问Hazel开发分支的源代码
you'll get access to the source code to the Hazel kind of development repository
开发分支那边，我几乎每天都在提代码，不是每天，但几乎每天都在做
the development branch which I'm working on pretty much every day, will not every day, but almost every day
上期视频中，我展示了Hazel引擎在开发分支中的具体进度
last video I actually showed like a bit of a bit of a tour of what the Hazel engine actually is in the development branch
那就是我已经实现了的细节展示，感觉你们对那个更感兴趣
and that was like a huge kind of little kind of show detail that I did, you guys are more interested in that
我注意到有些人想让我制作一期独立的视频来展示天使
I noticed that some people wanted me to like make a video actually showing the angel like a standalone video
就像是我们在引擎运行时中所拥有的一切，它能做什么，所有的特性
just kind of like a tour of what we actually have in the engine runtime and what everything, what it can actually do like all the features
如果你们感兴趣，一定要在下面留言，但如果现在就想看的话
if you guys interested in that, definitely leave a comment below, but if you want access to that like right now
你们可以直接在patreon上注册，来帮助支持我们这个系列，这样就可以访问源码构建那个
you can just sign up on patreon, conversations to channel helps about this series, and you'll get access to that source code and to that build
好了，不管怎样，回到这个，让我们说说渲染器接口吧，如何支持多个渲染接口
okay, so anyway, back to this, let's talk about renderer apis, how do we support multiple renderer apis
所以我认为你们要做的最重要的选择就是在编译或运行时，是否有这种支持
so I think the biggest choice that you have to make here is if you're going to kind of have this support during compilation or during runtime
那么我要说的是，比如我的意思，本质上你们可以通过多个渲染接口做的就是
so I kind of talk about like what I mean by that, essentially what you could do right with multiple rendering apis is
可以看到，在编译时，当我物理编译代码时，你们需要选择渲染接口，例如需要DirectX
you could see that at compile time when I physically compile my code, right, you need to select rendering api, for example I want DirectX
然后即将发生的就是，你们知道的，基本上
and then what will happen is you know via like essentially
如果定义或某些文件编译或未编译基于你们在这里设置的配置
if defs or certain files that either compiled or not compiled based on your kind of configuration set up here
你们可以选择我要用DirectX编译，这意味着Hazel将用DirectX构建，对吧
you can basically choose that like I am going to compile with DirectX, meaning that Hazel is going to be built with DirectX, right
如果你们想用OpenGL，那么添加编译时，就选择OpenGL，对吧
if you want to OpenGL, then add compile time, you choose OpenGL, right
然后所有被编译的文件都是特定于OpenGL的，对吧，然后你们在最终构建中使用OpenGL
and then all the files that are compiled are kind of OpenGL specific, right, and then you get OpenGL into your final build that
给你们一个更实际的例子吧，我的意思是，你们知道，你们可以
and to give you a more practical example, what I mean is like you know, you could have like
本质上就是你们把渲染接口分解成每个图元文件
essentially a file for each kind of you break down the rendering API and into primitive
所以你们就会有顶点缓冲区，索引缓冲区，纹理类，你们知道的，着色器类
so you have like a vertex buffer, an index buffer, texture class, you know shader class
然后你们要做的就是，创建个OpenGL着色器类，然后还有DirectX着色器类
and then what you do is you have like an OpenGL shader class, and then you have a DirectX shader class
并且其中只有一个会被编译，对吧，被编译的那个
and only one of those will be compiled, right, and the one that gets compiled
取决于你们的配置设置，取决于你们实际选择的渲染接口
depends on your configuration setup at which depends on which rendering API you've actually selected
所以你们就可以那样做，或者甚至可以有着色器的文件，比如Shader.cpp
so you can kind of do it like that, right, or you could even just have a shader of files, Shader.cpp
然后如果定义了，如果定义了DirectX，就编译这段代码
and then just if defs the kind of just, says you know if DirectX is defined, then compiled this chunk of code
否则如果OpenGL被定义，编译了这段代码，对吧，那就是另一种方法同样的原理，对吧
otherwise if OpenGL is defined, compiled this chunk of code, right, that's another way to do it same principle, right
只是没有将其分解成多个文件，而是将所有内容都放在一个文件中
just instead of breaking it up into multiple files, you have everything in one file
当然，那么就让我们来说说它的优点和缺点吧，好了，那么最大的缺点是什么
sure, so let's talk about the advantages and disadvantage of that, okay, so the biggest disadvantage, what's that with the disadvantages
因为我认为最明显的一点就是你们需要个独立构建的Hazel
because I think that's kind of the glaring obvious one is you need a separate build of Hazel
一个独立的构建，一个独立的物理二进制构建，以便实际选择你们想使用的接口
a separate build a separate physical binary build, in order to actually select which api you want to use
并且一旦你们用那个接口编译了代码，就那样了，你们就必须重新编译整个引擎
and once you compile your code with that api, that's it, you have to recompile the whole engine
或者释放引擎关于整个渲染器的渲染组件，如果你们真的想切换渲染接口的话
or release the rendering component of the engine about the whole renderer, if you actually want to switch rendering apis
想象一下，对吧，我的意思是正在运行，就像，啊，你们知道，我们写这个游戏就像
so picture this, right, I mean we're working, and we're like ah you know, we've written this game in like
我不知道，我们只是在做这个Sandbox项目，用OpenGL写的
I don't know, we're just working on this little Sandbox project, we've written it in OpenGL
我突然想看看它在DirectX中的样子，拿着啤酒，我用DirectX再次编译我的整个代码
suddenly I want to see what it looks like in DirectX, hold my beer while I compile my entire code again with DirectX
好吧，那不是，我不是，我真的不太热衷于那个，所以除了开发时间有点慢
right, that's not, I'm not, I'm really not a big fan of that, so apart from development times being kind of slow
特别是当真正在渲染器上运行时，那是人们没有意识到的比较重要的问题
especially when you're actually working on the renderer, that's another big thing that people don't realize
你们必须让它变得友好些，所以我的意思是，当你们实际开发渲染器
you have to make this develop a friendly, so what I mean by that is while you're actually developing the renderer
你们会如何处理这个，你们知道的，我已经完成了OpenGL实现
how you're gonna deal with this, well, you know I've finished the OpenGL implementation
现在我在做DirectX的实现，需要在它们之间切换，对吧，我需要在它们之间切换
now I'm working on the DirectX implementation, I need to switch between them, right, I need to switch between them
要知道视觉模仿是否相同，对吧，两个渲染器之间是否有差异
to know whether or not the visual parody is kind of the same, right, are there like discrepancies between the 2 renderers
DirectX和OpenGL看起来不一样吗？应该完全一样，如果看起来不一样，我就犯了个错
does DirectX look different to OpenGL, it shouldn't, right, it should be exactly the same, if it looks different, I've made a mistake
所以我需要来回反复比对，但是为了实现那个，就需要重新编译我的代码
so I'm going to have to go back, and forth them quite a bit, but to do that, I need to recompile my code
我的意思是，你们可以做很多事，OpenGL已经完成了，就可以把渲染代码放到模块中
and yeah I mean, there's a lot of things you could do, right, OpenGL is done, you could bring out all the rendering code into a module
所以那就像是在一个独立的组件中，在一个独立的module.dll文件中，对吧
so it's like in a separate kind of component in separate kind of module dll file whatever, right
然后如果你们想用OpenGL启动，我的意思是可以用DirectX或任何你们正在使用的渲染接口
and then if you want to kind of just launch with OpenGL, I mean you could just or DirectX or whatever one you're using
当然，你们就可以切换相应的dll文件，但那仍然意味着你们需要重新编译代码
you could just switch which one which dll file it uses, sure, but that still means that you need to recompile your code
它仍然意味着你们需要在编译时实现那个，对吧，不是我们想要做的事情，对吧
and it still means you need to do that kind of at compile time, right, not something we want to kind of do to do with that, right
所以那种决定是它属于那两个方面，你们想什么时候做那个决定
so that kind of decision is it falls into kind of those 2 areas, when do you want to make that decision
你们需要在编译时或运行时选择使用渲染接口呢
do you want to choose which renderer api use compile time or at runtime obviously
现在看来，在运行时显然是更好的，因为很多，你们知道的
right, now it seems like runtime is definitely the superior one, because a lot you know
为什么要提前做这个艰难的决定，如果你们能在最后做出决定，而且还不错的话，对吧
why have this hard decision that you have to make ahead of time, if you can just make it at the very end, and still be fine about that, right
并且我们马上就会讲到那个，但关于这个的另一个问题就是
and we'll kind of go into that in a minute, but the other thing with this is that
这样做的好处，最主要的好处就是性能，对吧，你们知道正在使用哪个渲染接口
the benefit the primary benefit of doing it, this way is essentially performance, right, you know which api you're using
你们基于那个渲染接口编译整个代码，对吧，那也就意味着没有任何运行时做的决定
you compile the whole code base with that api, right, which means that there's no kind of runtime decisions that ever get made
甚至一次都没有哦，就比如要使用这个渲染接口，我们需要实现这个
not even once, that say alright, well, if we're actually using this api, we need to do this
不可能，因为所有那些都是即时编译完成的，并且那就意味着在运行时
no, because all that stuff is done on the fly, all that stuff is done during compile time, and it means that during runtime
你们的代码、程序和引擎不需要做出任何决定，也就不再需要浪费时间
your code, your program, your engine doesn't have to make any decisions and waste time
因此不用浪费时间来做这些，比如当前使用的接口，或者你们想要使用的渲染接口，对吧
thus wait no waste time making those decisions, as to which api is currently in you, so which one you want to use, right
那不是必须要做的事情，因为已经在编译时之前完成了
that's not stuff, that actually has to be done, because it's already been done ahead of time at compile time
所以一旦它没那么多灵活性，就有可能给你们带来更好的性能，现在我们来说说后半部分
so once it gives you less flexibility, it does potentially give you more performance, now let's talk about the second half of things
那就是在运行时做那些决定，所以那意味着什么，本质上意味着编译所有东西，对吧
and that is making those decisions at runtime, so what does that mean, what that essentially means is that you compile everything, right
所以你们如果有OpenGL和DirectX实现，那么这两个实现就都会被编译
so you have an, you have an OpenGL implementation, you have a DirectX implementation, both of those implementations get compiled
通常你们实现这个的方式，直接就是，你们知道的，而不是ifdef之类，真不能只用ifdef
usually the way you do this again you could just, you know instead of ifdefs or whatever, you can't really do ifdefs
因为如果你们真的疯了，像个大疯子样，毕竟两个接口不可能共用一个着色器类
because you can't have like a shader class that suddenly does both, I mean, if you were really crazy and like a big psychopath
你们可能只是在每种函数中，对吧，在你们为着色器创建的每个函数中
you could probably just have like inside every kind of function that you have, right, inside every kind of function that you have for shaders
比如绑定着色器，或者你们知道的，上传统一变量之类的，那么可能就会检测，嘿
like bind shader, or you know upload uniforms or whatever, you could have an, if check that says, hey
如果这段代码用DirectX，这段用OpenGL，太疯狂了，我也不知道为什么会有人做那个
if it's DirectX on this code, if it's OpenGL on this code, that's just like a pathic, to be honest, I don't know why anyone will do that
但我已经看到过了，那就是为什么要提它，不要那样做，那么你们就可以这样做
but I have seen that, that's why I'm mentioning it, don't do that, you could do something like that
通常你们会把它分成多个文件，并且可能有很多方法可以实现这个
usually you break it up into multiple files, and potentially again many ways to do this
但如果你们在运行时做这个，可能会需要个基本的抽象类，就是纯虚类那种的
but potentially if you're doing it at a runtime, you'd probably have a base kind of abstract, you know, pure virtual kind of class
没有实现，可能也没存储任何数据，就像一个间接和抽象，如果你们愿意的话
that has no implementations, probably stores no data at all, just acts as like essentially a an indirection and abstraction, if you will
并且然后你们可能就会有两个类，或者一种渲染接口对应一个类
and then you have two classes or basically one class that breaks off per renderer api
那么可能会有，你们知道的，比如着色器，可能就会有OpenGLShader和DirectXShader
so you might have you know shader, and you might have OpenGLShader, and you might have DirectXShader
那些都是原始基类的，也就是那个Shader类的子类
those are both child classes, subclasses from that original base class, which is that just Shader class
对吧，由于它们都是纯虚类，那么在运行时，当实际创建着色器时，你们决定创建，对吧
right, and then since their pure virtual there, at runtime, when you actually create a shader, you decide upon creation, right
所以那样也不是真正的废，如果你们需要，这儿有很多方法可以让它变得更快
so it's not really like taxing, and there are ways to make it even faster, if you want
通过(epoll?)费尽心思想实现你们想要的，但基本上当你们创建着色器时
by pulling your hairs together or doing whatever you want, but essentially when you create a shader
它检查你们当前使用渲染接口，你们知道的，比如它是OpenGL
it checks to see what the current rendering api you're using actually is, and if it is you know OpenGL
然后它就会创建OpenGLShader并返回，如果是DirectX，就会创建DirectXShader，对吧
then it creates a new OpenGLShader, and returns that, if it's DirectX it creates a new DirectXShader, and returns that, right
但是基类类型返回的就是基类的类型，也就是Shader
but the base type is returning is the base class type, which is just Shader
所以当前阶段，你们在Sandbox中的所有客户端代码，或游戏中，对吧，都只能看到Shader
so you're all of your client code that's in Sandbox at this stage, right, or inside your game, that just sees Shader
就是那样，它只是个引用了Shader对象的指针
that's all, it is it's a pointer is some kind of reference to a Shader object
但不管它是OpenGLShader还是DirectXShader的实现细节，都被隐藏起来了
but the implementation detail of whether it's an OpenGLShader or DirectXShader is kind of hidden
我的意思是通常你们会提供方法来提取它，以防，因为你们知道，没有引擎接口是那样的
I mean usually you would provide ways to extract that just in case, because you know no engines api is that
你们就可以在里面做任何想做的事情，有点奇怪，我之前还没见过那种情况
that's kind of complete really that you can just do everything you want within that, it's a bit weird, I haven't really seen that before
我的意思是，如果这个取决于你们在做什么，如果是那种非常简单的
I mean if it depends what you're doing, if you're doing really simple stuff
你们不需要深入挖掘实现细节，但也有可能，因此可能会进行这种筛选
you shouldn't need to dig in deep into the implementation details, but you might, so you might have that kind of filtering through
但本质上客户端代码只看得到Shader，并不关心Shader是什么，因为如果你们想一想
but essentially the client code, just sees Shader, doesn't care what Shader is, because if you think about it
它会做什么，它会打开某种，创建个基于文件之类的新着色器
what does it do, it opens some kind of, creates a new shader based on like a file or something
它只要绑定着色器，上传统一变量数据，不需要知道你们使用的是DirectX还是OpenGL
it binds the shader, it uploads uniform data, it doesn't need to know if you're using DirectX OpenGL
因为那是你们在渲染接口中定义的接口，就在我几周前做的视频
because that's kind of the api you've defined in that rendering api, kind of video thing that I made a few weeks ago
可能是几个月前，我说过那个界线，对吧，在你们实际的渲染接口和渲染器之间的界线
a few months ago maybe,I talked about that line, right, between your actual renderer api, and then your actual renderer
渲染器只调用渲染接口，它不应该关心你们实际使用的是哪个实现
so the renderer just uses the rendering api, it doesn't, it shouldn't care which implementation you're actually using
它只是指定你们正在使用的渲染器，它应该是个简单的，比如只是查找着色器
which specific renderer you're using, it should just be a simple, it's just kind of just looking up shader
就比如创建着色器，上传这些统一变量，绑定着色器来渲染，对吧，就那么简单
and being like I want to create a shader, I want to upload these uniforms,  I want to bind the shader for rendering, right, simple as that
那么显然这里有个明显的事实，不是所有的渲染应用都能在所有平台上得到支持
so obviously there's the obvious fact here that if like not all rendering apps are supported on all platforms
我们一直在讨论DirectX和OpenGL作为两个主要渲染接口，只是为了这个例子，对吧
so DirectX, we've been talking about DirectX and OpenGL as our 2 main ones, just for the sake of this example, right
为了进行这种转换，OpenGL在几乎所有平台上都是可用的
for the sake of this kind of conversation, OpenGL is available on pretty much everything
而DirectX只适用于Windows和Xbox之类的微软产品，所以如果你们在Mac或Linux上编译
DirectX is only available on Windows and like Xbox and just Microsoft kind of products, so if you're compiling on Mac or Linux
DirectX代码就不会被编译，对吧，不会被编译，所以你们仍然需要ifdef，但也不只有ifdef
your DirectX code is not gonna compile, is it, no, it's not, so you still have to have like ifdef or, but or not even ifdef
我通常没有用ifdef，就只有独立的文件，所以我有Shader.h和Shader.cpp
the way I do what I don't usually have ifdefs, I just have separate files, so I have Shader.h and maybe Shader.cpp
就像基本抽象，然后在Platform特定的文件夹结构中，就有OpenGLShader.cpp和头文件
which is like my base abstraction, and then in my platform specific kind of folder hierarchy, I have OpenGLShader.cpp and h
然后还有DirectXShader.cpp和.h，对吧，不需要担心DirectX.h，而DirectXShader.cpp
and then DirectXShader.cpp and h, right, and DirectX, you don't really need to worry about the header file, but DirectXShader.cpp
那在Mac和Linux构建时是关闭的，并且可能除了Windows之外的所有构建都是关闭的
that is turned off for like Mac and Linux build, and probably all builds except for except for Windows at this, right right
所以它甚至不会编译，它只会在你们用VS为Windows生成项目时编译，对吧
so that's not even gonna compile, it's only gonna compile, when you generate the project for visual Studio, for Windows, right
如果你们的目标是Windows，那就会被编译，否则它就不会被编译的，好了
if you're targeting Windows, that gets compiled, otherwise it does not get compiled, okay
你们不用担心头文件，那样的话，很明显，然后你们实际上在通用的Shader.cpp中
and header file, you don't need to worry about, that way obviously oh, and then also usually in your actual kind of generic Shader.cpp
你们就有些Create函数，不会在运行时检查，只知道，当前使用的是哪个渲染接口
you have like some kind of create function, which doesn't, which does a runtime check, and it says, which rendering api are currently using
基本就像switch，如果是OpenGL，就执行那个，如果是DirectX，就会执行ifdefs中的那块
it's basically like a switch statement, if it's OpenGL, do that, otherwise if it's DirectX, and you have that block inside ifdefs
然后就返回新的DirectXShader，这样它就受到了保护，它只会为Windows编译
then you can return a new DirectXShader, so that way it's kind of protected, it's only going to compile for Windows
那就是DirectX的特定代码，我的意思，你们知道的，对于其他渲染接口，都是差不多的
that's specific code, and I mean, you know for other apis, it's kind of the same thing
所以你们不会在除了MacOS或iOS的其他平台编译Metal，所以就会通过配置把那些过掉
so you wouldn't really compile Metal on anything except for MacOS or iOS, right, so you have that stuff either filtered out by the configuration
如果它们是独立的CPP文件或ifdef，如果在一些通用文件中
if they're separate kind of cpp files or ifdeft, if they're in kind of common files
因为你们确实需要某种到公共文件的链接，不管怎样，我讲了很多
because you do need some kind of link to a common file at some rate in this, anyway, I've talked a lot
希望这个设计是有意义的，坐下来思考这个真的很酷，我也可以绘制关于这些的图表
hopefully this design is making sense, it's really cool to just sit down and think about this, I could draw a diagram of all this
我意识到我通常不会，因为我觉得这不是，我觉得这只是我在纸上写我的话
I realized that I usually don't, because I I feel like it's not, I feel like it's just me running down my words on paper
我想对一些人来说，直观地看东西还是挺不错的，所以让我知道你们对图表的看法
I think for some people, it's good to see things visually, so let me know what you think about diagrams in general
我来举个小杆看看，你们是否想要更多的图表，我的意思是我很少做这些
I'll run a little pole maybe to see if you guys want more diagrams, I mean I do them very rarely
不过如果视频是关于计划之类的，我通常就会那么做
usually I do them if the video is dedicated about planning or something like that
但我不这么做的主要原因只是因为这些东西在我的脑海里
but the main reason I don't is just because this stuff is, well it's in my mind
这有点简单，我所绘制的一切都只是我所说的话，所以如果你们想一想
it'skind of simple to the point where everything I would draw is just the words I'm saying, so if you just think about them
如果你们看不懂的话，可以重新看一遍，想象一下
and maybe rewatch that area, if you don't, if it doesn't make sense to you, and just visualize it
更不用说我们将看到背后的代码，所以那就是视觉辅助，那就是为什么我通常不费心
not to mention we're about to see the code behind this, so that will act as a visual aid, that's why I don't usually bother
但无论如何，我总是很乐意接受反馈，所以请让我知道你们的想法，这儿有几个类
but anyway, I'm always open to feedback obviously, so please let me know what you think, we have several classes here
我们今天不会对所有进行抽象，但是我想我们可以把顶点缓冲区抽象出来
we're not gonna abstract all of them today, I think we'll probably do the vertex buffer
因为我认为那个很容易，主要还是为了给你们些想法
because I think that's pretty easy, just to give you guys an idea
并且然后我想让你们做的作业也就是继续抽象着色器类
and then what I want you to do for homework is actually go ahead, and do the same thing with the shader class
抽象顶点数组类和索引缓冲区类
do the same thing with the vertex array class, do the same thing with the index buffer
事实上，我想我今天会抽象索引和顶点缓冲区，那就让我们来看看能做些什么
case in fact, I think I will do both the index buffer and the vertex buffer today, let's jump in and see what we can do
好了，那么这就是上期讲到的位置，如果直接运行这个，然后我们就会看到，有些什么
okay, so this is where we left off last time, if we just run this, then we'll see what we get
所以我们有这样一个在顶点位置和颜色之间插值的三角形
so we had this kind of triangle that was kind of interpolating between the vertex position colors that we had here
我们所做的只是在Application.cpp中，我们有这些OpenGL代码，显然不是我们想要保留的
what we did is just inside Application, we had all this OpenGL code, which obviously is not something that we ever want to keep
对吧，这只是一个如何尽快把这些东西显示在屏幕上的例子
right, this is just kind of an example of how to kind of get this stuff on screen as soon as possible
但我们现在想做的是让它通用，对吧，让它通用，你们知道，我想要能够像
but what we want to do now is make this generic, right, make this generic in the sense that you know, I want to just be able to like
其他这些代码都不知道渲染接口是什么，对吧，它真不知道，你们知道的，它只有层
none of this other code has any idea of what a rendering api is, right, it doesn't really, you know, it's got layers
它知道EventDispatcher，或者有些不是渲染接口特定的代码，而不是就像这样创建
it's got EventDispatcher or it's got stuff that is not render api specific, instead of creating stuff like this
比如这里就有定义我们顶点缓冲区的gl代码
and having gl code here that for example defines our vertex buffer
而我想做的，本质上就是创建VertexBuffer，对吧
what I essentially want to be able to do is create a VertexBuffer, right
本质上，你们知道的，你们实现这个的方式可能是不同的取决于选择如何实现
which essentially you know and the way you do this might be different depending on how you choose implemented
但是你们知道的，我们可能会做比如VertexBuffer::Create()，可能会接收vertices，就像这样
but you know we'll probably want to do something like VertexBuffer::Create(), we'll probably want to take in you know the vertices like this
也许绘制模式也像内存存储类型一样，因为它是STATIC，DYNAMIC和STREAM之类的
maybe the draw mode as well like the memory storage type, because is whether it's static or dynamic or streaming or anything like that
但本质上，我们想要把这里的所有vertices定义都作为VertexBuffer，就是那样
but essentially we want to probably take in the whole kind of vertices definition that we have here as a VertexBuffer, and that's kind of it
然后在绘制时，我们可能会做些操作，比如buffer.Bind()，搞定，我们希望它是这样的
and then when it's time to draw, we just probably do something like that x like buffer.Bind(), and that's done, we want it to be like this
因为我们实际上不想包含glad之类的库，就我们所知，这可以使用DirectX
because we don't actually want to include glad or anything like that, this could be using DirectX for all we know
并且至于实现这些的这种方式，显然我们不仅仅在VertexBuffer中有OpenGL代码
and this kind of way of doing things, and obviously we don't just have the OpenGL code inside VertexBuffer
它也会返回我们实际上选择的渲染接口的实现，并且我们实际上也会创建这些
it returns an implementation of which api we've actually chosen, and we'll actually create all of them
对吧，现在就来看看那是什么样子的，好了，酷，所以那就是我们的目标
right, now and see what that looks like, okay, cool, so that's kind of the goal
你们通常会做的就是让这个返回些指针
usually you do kind of usually this would return some sort of pointer
我通常直接会在这里返回一个完全原始的指针，对吧，然后它会是
I usually just like returning a completely raw pointer in here, right, and then it's gonna be up to like
如果你们确实有个带有引用计数之类的引擎，那么我可能就会返回引用
if you do have an engine with a reference counting or something like that, I would probably return a ref
因为我们现在还没有那个，我就直接让Create返回一个原始指针
since we don't have that at the moment, I'm just going to have create return a raw pointer
然后这将是客户端的工作来实际管理它，不管他们喜欢通过将原始指针推入共享指针
and then it's gonna be the client's job to actually manage that, however they like either by shoving that raw pointer into like a shared pointer
或者通常我们在这里要做的就是把它放到一个唯一指针中，好了，那么就让我们来看看
or usually like what we're gonna do here is just kind of putting it into a unique pointer, okay, so let's take a look at
我们如何做这样的事情，这就是这个接口的目标，那么在Renderer中，创建一个新项
how we can do something like this, this is kind of the goal for the api, so over here in renderer, I'm gonna make a new item
并且实际上，我就直接叫它Buffer.h，现在你们可能会想，好吧，这是不是VertexBuffer
and I'm actually just gonna call this Buffer.h, now you might be like well, okay, is this gonna be the VertexBuffer
为什么要叫Buffer，我叫它Buffer就是因为我不喜欢创建大量文件
why you calling a Buffer, the reason I'm calling a Buffer is because I I'm not a huge fan of creating 1,000,000 files
我认为这不是必要的，我认为它减慢了你们的构建时间，并且它让代码更难阅读
I think that it's not that necessary, I think that it like it slows down your build times, it makes code harder to read through
如果想和别人分享你们的代码，那么你就必须给他们大量文件，那确实有点烦
if you want to like share your code with someone, you have to give them 1,000,000 files, it's just a bit annoying
所以我肯定会比如创建多个文件，你们可以看到实际上我这里已经有不少文件了
so I definitely like creating more than one file, you can see I've actually got quite a few here
那将来会少些吧，但也可能不会，不过对于Buffer这样的东西
that might get collapsed in the future, but probably not, but for things like Buffer
我不喜欢用VertexBuffer和IndexBuffer这样的类，它们都是缓冲区，只是不同类型的缓冲区
I don't really like having a VertexBuffer and IndexBuffer kind of class, they're both buffers, they're just different types of buffers
所以应该把它们放在一个文件，显然这只是我的观点，不赞同随你们，但那就是我要做的
so you should just have them in one file, this is clearly just my opinion, feel pretty disagree with it, but that's kind of what I do
好了，我比如做些事情，基本上喜欢创建这样的代码，然后直接在一个文件中创建多个类
okay, I like to do something, I basically like to create code like this, and then just have multiple classes in one file
这只是让它更简单，然后你们知道的，我将对纹理进行同样的处理
it just makes it easier, okay, and then you know, I'll do the same for texture for example
所以这儿每个渲染接口都会有一个文件叫做Texture，然后在那里，就会有2DTexture
so there'll just be one file per rendering api called like texture essentially, and then in there, we'll have 2D textures
你们知道的，3D纹理，立方体贴图之类的东西，所有用纹理做的东西都在一个文件里
you know 3 textures cube maps that kind of stuff, everything you do with texture have all in one file
而不是必须有一个单独的文件，每个类型的纹理
instead of having to have a separate, a separate file for each kind of type of texture
因为在我看来，那太烦了，不管怎样，那么我们就有两个，包含pch和Buffer
because that's just annoying, in my opinion, anyway, so we have both of these will include our pch, we'll include our Buffer class
然后是我创建的头文件，并且然后是namespace Hazel，让我们来说说这儿我们需要什么
and then I'll header file I made, and then we'll have a namespace Hazel, and then let's talk about what we need here
那么这个就是我们的纯虚接口，对吧，我的意思是这里没有实现
so this is our pure virtual interface, right, what I mean by that is there is no implementation here
并且这儿绝对没有成员，完全没有数据成员，这个应该不占存储空间
and there is absolutely no members, no data members at all, this this should take up 0 storage
显然它会占用一个字节，当初始化时，必须有它的类，但没有成员，就不占用任何存储空间
obviously it'll take up one bytes, when we initialize it, it has to its class, but it's got no members it takes up no storage
它就像是这些被调度的虚函数的尾巴
it's literally just like a retail of just functions of those virtual functions that get dispatched to
不管是哪种子类，实际上都实现了这个接口，对吧
whatever kind of subclasses actually realizes this implementation, right
这种抽象，所以我们就不需要构造函数之类的
this kind of abstraction, so we don't really need a constructor or anything like that
不过确实需要个虚析构函数，通常是空的，对吧，我们会直接实现这个，我想对于这两个
you do need to have a virtual destructor, usually this is just empty, right, we'll do this straight away, I think for both of these
所以你们会知道它是如何实现的，希望通过实现两次
so you're gonna get the idea of how it's implemented, and hopefully by implementing it twice
就像我在这里，你们就会明白，需要做什么去实现Shader，然后就只需要定义接口
as I am here you'll kind of see, what you need to do to implement the stuff of shader, and then we just define the interface
那么VertexBuffer，VertexBuffer的功能是什么，我们肯定需要一些绑定函数
so VertexBuffer, what are the functions of a VertexBuffer, well we definitely want to have some sort of like binding functions
那么就是virtual void Bind()，我们需要能够为渲染绑定顶点缓冲，或者直接放到顶点数组
so virtual void bind, right, we want to be able to bind the vertex buffer for rendering, or if we want to put into a VertexArray
关于这个在顶点数组上的原理，顺便说下，我们以后会讲到，因为那有点不同
the way that this will actually work with the vertex array, by the way, we will talk about that later, because that's a bit different
那实际上是更具体的接口，不像你们知道的，比如？？？，处理这些就是不同的
and that is actually a bit more api specific, unlike you know, drug devs for example, which deals with the stuff differently
那么就是Bind()和Unbind()，我肯定会比如创建SetData()和UploadData()这些虚函数
so Bind Unbind, I definitely like to have some kind of like SetData UploadData things are virtual
如果要实现的话，可能就是virtual void SetData()，然后在这儿就有些，最后关于构造函数
if you would write it, you do like virtual void SetData, and then you'd have your stuff here, and now finally for the construction
我们实际上想做的就是，你们会注意到，如果我能找到，这个在哪儿
what we actually want to do is you'll notice is, if I can find where this stuff is
我们实际上需要，你们会看到想要的是实际的顶点数据，对吧，还有VertexAttribPointer
we want to actually, you'll see that what we kind of want is the actual vertex data, right, VertexAttribPointer as well
和顶点数组有关，不是我们现在需要做的，但这儿这部分代码
something to do with vertex arrays, not really something we want to do right now, but just this kind of chunk of code here
我们需要把vertices赋给这个，那对这个来说是完全错误的，对吧，但是不想创建构造函数
we need to actually give the vertices to this, that was completely the wrong thing to this, right, however I don't want to create a constructor
因为如果我创建了构造函数的话，那就意味着我需要选择我需要的类型
because if I create a constructor, that means that I need to actually choose which type I want
所以我要做的就是创建个静态VertexBuffer，那就是我之前说的，我们返回的是一个实指针
so what I'm actually going to do is create a static VertexBuffer, and again that's what I said, we're returning a real pointer
这就像是在你的引擎里有一个引用计数系统，我们现在还没有
it would be like maybe some kind of referview had a reference counting system inside your engine which we don't at the moment
那么就是static VertexBuffer* Create()，这儿这个就是我的构造函数
a static VertexBuffer* Create(), and here this is like my constructor
所以可以接收各种参数，并且它是静态，所以就不属于这个类，至于VertexBuffer* Create()
so I take in everything I want here right, and it's static, so it doesn't actually belong to this class, VertexBuffer* Create()
然后可能就会传入vertices，然后是uint32_t，也就是size，顺便说下，可以直接用size_t
and then I'll probably just take in my vertices, and then a uint32_t, which is my kind of size, could just use a size_t, by the way
但是我们就用uint32_t，好了，我们继续，搞定，这两个类很像的
but we'll use uint32_t, okay, there we go, done, this is very similar in both of these
只不过这会返回IndexBuffer*，我们可能会传入uint32_t，也就是我们的indices
except this returns a IndexBuffer instead, and we'll probably have a uint32_t, which is our indices
对吧，所以我们有无符号的32位整型，我们可能会直接用32位整型，也就是int32 indices
right, so we have an unsigned 32bit integer, we'll probably go just gonna stick with 32bit integer 32bit indices
16位整型绝对是你们以后可以做的优化之一，但更多时候不止在
for now16 bit is definitely an optimization you could make in the future, but more often than not
如果你们想渲染东西，想要一个简单的实现，你们知道的，32位整型也是可以的
if you're trying to render things, and you're trying to just have a simple implementation, just you know 32 bit is just the way to go
否则你们就会用完索引，好了，酷，这看起来很好，现在我们只需要创建这两个Create函数
otherwise you'll just run out of indices, okay, cool, this looks pretty good to me, now we just need to create these two Create functions
所以它们很简单，我们把它复制到这，这个就是VertexBuffer* Create()
so they're pretty easy, we just drag this over here, this is gonna be VertexBuffer* Create()
对吧，然后同样的，我直接用VA帮助创建这个实现，已经有了，漂亮
right, and then we do the same thing, I'll just use visual assist here to make this implementation for me, we've got this here, wonderful
现在我们需要做的是决定，在这个Create函数中，我们决定当前使用的是哪个接口
now what we need to do is actually decide, in this function, in this create function, we decide which api we're currently using
那么我们渲染器使用的什么接口呢，以及类类型是，以及我们实例化并返回的类类型，对吧
so what api our renderer is using, and thus which which class type, which actual kind of class we instantiate and return, okay
它会很明显地将它转换为基类型，所以我们不会返回实际的派生类型，但那就是目的
it's going to kind of obviously cast it to the base type here, so we're not returning the actual derived type, but that's the intention
酷，好了，那么为了有类返回，我们实际上需要创建它们，因为我们现在暂时处理OpenGL
cool, okay, so in order to have classes to return, we actually need to make them, so since we're kind of dealing with OpenGL for now
那么在Platform/OpenGL中，我要添加一个新项，就是OpenGLBuffer.h
inside Platform/OpenGL, I'm going to add a new item, and this is going to be called OpenGLBuffer.h
那么你们可以看到，所有与OpenGL相关的东西，我这儿都是用的OpenGL前缀
so you can see that everything that is kind of OpenGL related, I'm starting with the OpenGL kind of prefix here
然后Buffer是类的类型或者说类上面的文件名，在实际的泛型渲染器中
and then buffer is kind of the type of class or rather the file name over the class, inside the actual kind of generic renderer
所以就添加这个，也就是渲染接口，我们还有命名空间，也要包含来着通用渲染接口的文件
so we add this, which is the rendering api, we have our namespace, we include the file from the generic kind of rendering api
也就是这个(Buffer.h)，对吧，然后就创建OpenGLVertexBuffer类，继承自VertexBuffer
which is this one, right, and then we make our OpenGLVertexBuffer class, which is a VertexBuffer
好了，然后我们要做的是实现那个文件，我们创建的那个类，我们在这里已经实现了
okay, and then what we do here is we actually implement that file, right, so that class that we've created this, we implemented here
显然我们不需要Create，就可以把它放在这里，把它作为虚析构函数
so we don't need the Create obviously, so we can take this, we can put it in here, we can keep this as a virtual distractor
因为它已经是虚函数了，这样的话，我们就知道它是虚函数，然后Bind和Unbind
just because it's already virtual, and this way, we know that it is virtual and smart correctly, and then Bind and Unbind
顺便说一下，我应该写const，我们在这里的实现中实现了这些东西
which by the way, I should have made const, and this stuff we just kind of implement over here inside our implementation
在这种情况下，也就是这个OpenGLVertexBuffer，你们可以在这里放任何想要的数据
which is the OpenGLVertexBuffer, in this case, you can put anything else you want here
对吧，那么显然需要m_RendererID，创建了么，不记得了，对哦，没有，就是uint32_t
right, so obviously we're going to put a RendererId, did I make int, I don't remember, yeah no, I didn't, it's just a uint32
通常会创建个RendererId类型，会在另一期Shader类中提到，刚刚创建了m_RendererID
usually I'd make a RendererId type, we'll talk about that in another time, in the Shader class, we just had a RendererID
所以我们保存了这个，在实际的实现中保存这个，没有在这(VertexBuffer)保存任何数据
so we store this, you'll note, we store this in the actual implementation, we don't store anything in here at all
我们不应该在这里保存任何数据，对吧，这只是一个接口，不应该保存任何数据
you shouldn't, we shouldn't store anything here, right, this is just an interface, just should not store any data
这才是数据实际保存的地方，所以有个uint32_t数据，也就是我们的RendererID
this is where the data is actually stored, so we have a uint32_t, which is our RendererID
我们还会创建个OpenGLBuffer.cpp文件，包含hzpch.h，在这儿能做的就是，哦，差点忘了
we'll make an OpenGLBuffer.cpp file, OpenGLBuffer.cpp, which will include our pch, and what we can do here is just oh and one thing
我肯定需要创建个构造函数，它接收的参数和Create()函数是一样的
that I definitely want to make is a constructor, which takes in exactly what our Create function takes in
所以在Buffer.cpp中，我们有这个Create函数，只接收vertices和size参数
so inside Buffer, we have this Create function, which takes in vertices and size
那就是我需要构造函数接收的参数，对吧，就是vertices和size
that's what I want the constructor to take in, okay, vertices and size
现在让我们用VA来创建这些实现，顺便说一下，我不是由它赞助的，只是习惯使用它
now let's create these implementations using visual assist, who by the way I'm not sponsored by, just I just like using it
然后在这里，我们要做一些事情，好了，那么首先，我的意思是，这就是VertexBuffer类
and then over here, we're gonna do some things, okay, so first of all, yeah I mean look this is the VertexBuffer class
这就是我们即将绘制的三角形，在游戏引擎中，VertexBuffer类非常详细，非常大，对吧
this is we're currently drawing a triangle, in a game engine, the VertexBuffer class is quite exhaustive, it's quite big, right
你们就需要做很多决定，比如是否在CPU端保留这个顶点信息
there's a lot of decisions you want to make, such as whether or not you retain this vertex information on the CPU side
如果你们在做RayPicking(光线拾取)之类的，可能会需要这么做
which you might want to do, if you're doing things like RayPicking
或者在重置鼠标拾取之类的操作，也有狠有比如碰撞之类的不同操作
or in a recasting 2 mouse pick stuff like that, there's tons of different like collision whatever
在VertexBuffer中，你们可能想做很多不同的事情
there's tons of different things that you actually might want to do from a VertexBuffer
我们现在要做的是我们可能不会保留它，至少不会复制并保存在这里
what we'll do for now is we'll probably won't retain this, at least we won't copy it and keep it here
但我认为我们在这里真正需要的是，我不知道，我的意思是我们真的不需要任何东西
but what we do need over here really I think is, well I don't know, I mean we don't really need anything to be honest
并且size这些参数会在构造函数中处理，那么这儿是我们的实际代码
the size and all that stuff will handle in the constructor, so this is the actual code we have here
我们仍然会使用GenBuffers，而不是CreateBuffers，但也没关系，说实话，可能只是切换
and we're still using GenBuffers not CreateBuffers, but that's okay, we could probably just switch, to be honest
我可能就会调用glCreateVertexBuffers，或者glCreateBuffers
if I can do something called glCreateVertexBuffers or glCreateBuffers
对吧，基本上也就是这两个合在一起，那么，害，似乎忘了函数签名
right, which is basically these 2 steps in one, so and I don't remember the function signature
我想只是在某些情况下可能会需要ArrayBuffer，不知道，我就去查下这个
I think it's just that we'll need ArrayBuffer at some case, I don't know I'm just gonna look this up
那么CreateBuffers，glad，CreateBuffers，这里有签名，好了，实际上只有buffers和size
so CreateBuffers, glad, CreateBuffers, there's a function signature, okay, cool, so it actually does just have the buffers and a size
好了，那么回到这儿，我们有了size和m_RendererID，对吧，酷，还需要包含glad.h，继续
okay, so back here, we have our size and we have our RendererID, all right, cool, we also need to include glad.h, and there we go
我们创建了缓冲区，在这个阶段不管它是什么类型的，不管怎样，当设置缓冲区数据时
so we create our buffer, doesn't matter what kind of buffer it is at this stage, anyway, when we actually set our buffer data though
那时就会为VertexBuffer用ARRAY_BUFFER，为IndexBuffer用ELEMENT_ARRAY_BUFFER了
that's when we will use a GL_ARRAY_BUFFER for VertexBuffer, and GL_ELEMENT_ARRAY_BUFFER for IndexBuffer
那么就不会再使用sizeof(vertices)了
so we have, we can't use size of vertices anymore
很明显，它只是个指针，我们使用size和vertices，这里又会用到GL_STATIC_DRAW了
obviously it's just a pointer, we use size, we use vertices, and we for now again hard-code GL_STATIC_DRAW
好了，那么我们继续，然后我们还会在析构函数中，我们还没有，让我们看看
okay, so there we go, then we'll also have in the destructor, which we haven't, let's see
那么这个就不需要在这里实现了，而是需要在这实现，并且然后直接就是glDeleteBuffers了
so this needs to not be implemented here anymore, we need to take this and implement it here, and then this will just glDeleteBuffers
因为不想保留那个，这里glBindBuffer()，那么就是GL_ARRAY_BUFFER和m_RendererID
because we don't want to retain that glBindBuffer, let's see, so GL_ARRAY_BUFFER and m_RendererID
然后Unbind，可能不会经常用，但会解除绑定，好了，酷，那么继续，非常简单的类
and then Unbind, which we probably will not use that often, but we will unbind it then, okay, cool, so there we go, very simple class
只是简单地创建缓冲区，上传它们，然后我们可以为渲染绑定它们，并且我会实现这些
just simply creates buffers, uploads them, and then we can bind them for rendering, and I'll do all of that kind of stuff
好了，回到Application类中，让我们试一下，看看会发生什么，那么我们仍然有vertices
okay, so back inside our application class, let's try that out and see what happens, so we still have our vertices
我们不需要再生成这个了，如果回到这儿，我们就可以代替m_VertexBuffer
we don't need to generate this anymore, if I go back to here, we can instead of having unsigned VertexBuffer
我们可以直接去掉那个，实际上会有个指向VertexBuffer的唯一指针
we can get rid of that and actually have a unique pointer to a VertexBuffer
并且那就是我们的m_VertexBuffer，酷，那么然后在这里，我还必须包含这个
and that will be our m_VertexBuffer, cool, so then over here, and I'll have to include this
所以基本上一样的，除了VertexBuffer，那么在这，有个m_VertexBufffer，我喜欢用reset
so basically the same as that except VertexBuffer, so now over here, we have a VertexBuffer, I like to just use reset
所以我上次用过，对吧，然后我们把这个放在这，显然先有数据(vertices)，然后是size
so I used last time, yeah I did, and then we put this in here, obviously we have the data first and the size second here
那应该没什么问题吧，好了，很明显没用，不好意思，问题不大，这里直接就是Buffer
that should be okay, okay, that clearly didn't work, sorry, it's not bad, it's Buffer, it's just Buffer
好了，我们继续，然后差不多就那样了，我的意思是我们可能应该绑定它
okay, and there we go, and then that's kind of it, I mean we probably should bind it
我不确定Create是否绑定它，那就是问题所在，我想我们可以运行这个，看看会发生什么
I'm actually not sure if create create binds it or not, that's kind of the problem, I guess we can run this and see what happens
但那应该很有趣，我不认为我们漏了什么，我们还需要实现BufferData吗
but yeah that'll be interesting, I don't think we're doing anything else, are we still doing buffer data
所以我不应该那样做，让我们直接取消那个编译吧，反正都失败了
so I shouldn't actually do that, let's just cancel that build, I've failed anyway
好了，为什么我失败了，好吧，Create什么都没做，我们还没把这个讲清楚
okay, why I fail, okay, so create of course create does nothing yet, we haven't sort of this out yet
所以你们实际上应该做的是，我们没有渲染器类，有点烦人，我们下次一定要设置那个
so what you actually should do is, we don't have a renderer class, which is kind of annoying, we should definitely set that up next time
因为我们真的需要，因为有些通用渲染器命令，比如你们知道的Clear和ClearColor之类的
because we really need to, because we also have kind of generic renderer commands like Clear and ClearColor that you know
在大多数情况下，你们可能会关联到一个帧缓冲区
in most cases, you could probably associate to a frame buffer
但是在你们的渲染器中，也有些有用的函数作为渲染器命令
but also useful functions to have inside your actual renderer as renderer commands
在那个Renderer类中，我们可能有个接口的切换，所以如果你们使用的是OpenGL或DirectX
and inside that Renderer class, we probably have a switch for the api, right, so if you're using like OpenGL or DirectX it would kind of
渲染器应该为你们提供这些，对吧，所以我们现在要做的就是创建Renderer类
the renderer is what should kind of have that for you, right, so what we'll do right now is we'll create a Renderer class
直接就是Renderer，对吧，这对今天来说只是一丢丢，但基本上
which is just called a Renderer, right, this is going to be so brush for today, but basically
它要做的就是创建个枚举类RendererAPI，然后这个就是None
what it's going to do is have an enum class RendererAPI, right, and then this is going to be None
就像你在无头文件运行，或者只是不想，如果你们可能在做不需要Rendererr的单元测试
which is like if you're running headless, or if you just don't want to have, if you may be doing unit tests that don't require Rendererr
你们比如在构建机器上运行它们之类的
and you're running them on like a build a build machine or something like that
它甚至可能没有你们想要测试的显卡
which might not even have a graphics card in it that you want to test with
那么就有了None，然后是OpenGL，在以后，你们知道的，可能有Direct3D或Vulcan之类的
so you have None and then you have OpenGL, and then in the future you know we'll probably have like Direct3D or Vulcan whatever
但这两个显然是我们现在有的
but these are kind of the 2 that we obviously have right now
好了，这个可能需要以某种静态状态保存，因为我说过，它非常简短
okay, this needs to be stored in some kind of static state probably, again since I said it's gonna be really brief
我们基本上要做的就是在Renderer类中有个静态的RendererAPI，对吧
essentially what we're gonna do is just have a static RendererAPI inside the Renderer class, right
也就是s_RendererAPI，我们马上就会看到，好了，然后在马上创建的cpp文件中
which is the s_RendererAPI, we'll just see, okay, and then inside the cpp file, which I'll now have to create
既然已经这样做了，没问题，Renderer.cpp，包含hzpch和Renderer.h，namespace Hazel
since I just did it this way, which is fine, renderer.cpp, include our pch, will include our Renderer.h, namespace Hazel
这显然是我们可以在运行时设置的东西，但现在只会设置成RendererAPI::OpenGL，对吧
and then this for now clearly something that we can set at runtime, but for now this just gets set to RendererAPI::OpenGL, okay
所以我们在这里很难创建它，显然你们可以在运行时设置它
so we are hard creating it here, obviously it's something that you could definitely set at runtime
事实上，我们会为它添加个获取方法，我们会有公共内联方法 RendererAPI
in fact we're going to add a get up for it, so we'll have inline, public private, inline RendererAPI
我不知道，比如GetRendererAPI()，可能直接就是GetAPI()，老实说，在Renderer中
I don't know, GetRendererAPI(), probably just GetAPI(), to be honest, inclue inside the Renderer
你们可以直接调用当前接口之类的，然后这个是静态函数，直接返回s_RendererAPI
you could call a current api or whatever, and then this will just be static, and it will just return s_RendererAPI
好了，酷，如果你们想设置这个，然后还可以用SetApi()做同样的事情，很明显
okay, cool, and then you could also do SetApi that does the same thing, if you want to set this
你们需要在Application中创建Renderer和上下文前设置，本质上是在创建窗口之前
and obviously if you set it before you create the Renderer and the context in Application, essentially before you create the window and everything
它应该使用那个接口，好了，酷，现在我们已经在我们的Buffer类中了
it should use that chosen api, okay, cool, so now that we've got that inside our open side just our Buffer class
就这儿，所以我们直接包含Renderer
which is over here, we will include, we're already in here, so we can just include the Renderer
然后执行switch，检查Renderer::GetAPI，如果它是None，那么可能不会返回任何东西
and then we do a switch segment, and we check Renderer::GetAPI, okay, so if it is None, you know then we'll probably won't return anything
所以暂时就返回nullptr，我们可能会有一个什么都不做的实现
so return null point up for now, we probably will have an implementation that does nothing though
否则这个崩溃，所以我们可以在这种情况下直接断言
otherwise this purple crash, so we could just assert in this case
说实话，我们可能那样做，HZ_CORE_ASSERT(false, "RendererAPI::None is not supported")
to be honest, we might do that, HZ_CORE_ASSERT(false, ""), and we'll say RendererAPI::None is not supported
它目前不受支持，然后我们会返回nullptr，当然对于OpenGL，我们会把这个移到这里
it's currently not supported, and then we will return non pointer, and then for OpenGL of course, so we'll kind of move this over here
我们可以，把这个向前回点，会返回OpenGLVertexBuffer，里面有vertices和size
we will, we can move this back a bit, we will return a new OpenGL vertex buffer with the vertices and the size
所以我只是想弄明白这个的所有原理，对吧
so I really just kind of making sense how this all works, right
然后很明显，在这里，返回nullptr，我们也可以在这里有个断言表示它失败了
and then obviously over here the return null pointer, and we could just, you know also have an assert here essentially that says it failed
也就是说，如果你说，它的值不在这里，我们可以让一个烤箱断言这有假的未知品牌的reapi
that's if somehow you said, it to a value that's not here, so just we can just have a oven assert this has false Unknown RendererAPI
好了，然后OpenGLBuffer.h当前是我们需要包含的文件
okay, and then OpenGLBuffer is of course something that we need to include
那么就是Hazel，它实际上在哪儿，就是Platform，它没有在Hazel中，显然没有
so Hazel, where is it actually, Platform, this Platform is not in Hazel, apparently not
那么就是OpenGLBuffer.h，对吧，然后很明显，如果比如，对吧，这儿复制几行
OpenGLBuffer, right, and then obviously if for example, right, this will share some line here
那么比如，我们已经有了Direct3D/Direct3DBuffer.h或DirectXBuffer.h之类的，对吧
if for example we you know had Direct3D and Direct3DBuffer or DirectXBuffer or whatever you called it, right
由于那个只支持Windows，你们知道的，会做些比如#if HZ_PLATFORM_WINDOWS之类
that since that's Windows only, you would do something like you know, if HZ_PLATFORM_WINDOWS or something
你们会做这个，否则就不会包含，这样的话，你们仍然可以在MacOS上编译这个类
you would do this, otherwise you wouldn't, right,and that way you'd still be able to compile this class on like MacOS
同样的，如果你们知道，这是DirectX而不是OpenGL，也可以用它来处理这个
and then same with this, if this was you know DirectX instead of OpenGL, you could surround this case specifically by that
对吧，这样的话，DirectX代码就会被忽略，在不支持它的平台上根本不会编译
right, and in that way obviously the DirectX code is ignored and not compiled at all on platforms that do not support it
好了，那么我们继续，就是那样，差不多就是那样了
okay, so there we go, that is that, and then that's pretty much it
显然对于IndexBuffer，我们需要做一样的处理，那么就这儿，OpenGLBufffer仍然在这儿
obviously for IndexBuffer, we need to do the exact same thing, so I'll come over here, OpenGLBuffer is still the file here
这就是OpenGLIndexBuffer，它有我们的indices和size，我想我们还没有创建类
this will be OpenGLIndexBuffer, which has our indices and our size, still not a class that we've created yet I guess
但是，耶，我们继续，完全一样的代码，对吧，我只是想把它敲过去
but yeah there we go, exact same code, right, I just like to tap this across
酷，那么我们现在要去创建那个IndexBuffer了，所以我们就直接复制并粘贴这个
cool, so now I will have to create that IndexBuffer I guess, so if we copy and paste this
我们就叫它IndexBuffer，很明显继承IndexBuffer，如果看看Buffer.h，可以找出些原因
we'll call this our IndexBuffer, and obviously it will be an IndexBuffer, if we go to, Buffer, and not trying out for some reason
但如果我们到这里，就可以直接复制这个，把它粘贴到这儿，又会是一期很长的视频
but if we go here, we can steal this, copy it, paste it here, there's gonna be another long episode
幸运，伙计们，好了，这就是IndexBuffer，看起来不错，然后这儿，我们可以复制粘贴这个
lucky, you guys, okay, IndexBuffer, looks good to me, and then if we go over here, we can basically copy and paste this
我要代码中的Vertex替换成Index，然后显然我们需要在这里得到适当的代码
I'm just going to replace code here from Vertex to Index, alright, and then obviously we need to get the appropriate code here
也就是glBufferData，变成了ELEMENT，但我们可能还需要绑定它，我们一会儿再看
which is that glBufferData, this becomes ELEMENT, all right, but we might still need to bind it, we'll check that out in a minute
我想会一起学习那个，indices，OpenGLIndexBuffer，把这改成ELEMENT_ARRAY_BUFFER
we'll both learn that together I guess indices, and then um OpenGLIndexBuffer, we change this to the ELEMENT_ARRAY_BUFFER
其他的都是一样的，好了，酷，通常我喜欢做的是把这些分开，因为它们都在一个文件中
everything else says the same, okay, cool, and then usually what I like to do is just kind of separate this, because it's all in one file
你们可能需要看到，我想用这样的分隔，所以你们知道的，有时我基本上这样做
and you kind of want to see kind of the, I guess separation of these 2 things, so you know sometimes I do something like this essentially
我不知道，它的格式是不同的，我只是根据我的心情改变它
and I don't know it, the formatting for this varies, I just kind of change it up depending on my mood
但现在我想我可能会这样做，这是我们的IndexBuffer，然后这是我们的VertexBuffer
but right now I guess I'll do something like this, which is just our index buffer, and then this will be our vertex buffer
有时我也会在头文件中这样做，这样很明显，我们有这两种实现
and sometimes I do this in the header file as well, just so that it's super obvious, where we have those 2 kind of implementations
顺便说一下，你可能不需要写三四行，但你可以随意写
you probably don't need to have like 3 4 lines to take this up by the way, but do as you wish
好了，酷，那么继续，我们在这里多了一个，因为顶点的线太多了或者说多了个字符
okay, cool, so there we go, we've got an extra one here, because I guess the vertex was too many lines or rather one more character
不管怎样，好了，我们漏了一些东西，因为我把它放进了Vertex的区域，可爱
anyway, so there we go, we're missing something, because I put this into the vertex spot lovely
看起来很好，如果我们回到Buffer.cpp，你们就可以检查确保这都编译了，它确实编译了
yeah that looks pretty good to me, if we go back to the Buffer.cpp file, you can check to make sure this all compiles, and it does
然后回到Application，这里的IndexBuffer不是unsigned int，这里会有个IndexBuffer实例
and then back inside Application, instead of having that IndexBuffer as just to unsigned int here, we'll have an IndexBuffer instance here
好了，酷，为了实现这个，我需要包含Buffer，不过已经包含了，因为它们都在一个文件中
okay, cool, and then for that to happen I need to include Buffer, which I already am, because they're both in one file
就很简单奈斯了，为了做这个，不管怎样，都是代替glGenBuffers这些，还有glBufferData
which is lovely, nice and easy, we're in to do this, anymore, instead of glGenBuffers and all that stuff, and glBufferData
我们直接创建indices，然后可以看到m_IndexBuffer.reset(IndexBuffer::Create(indices, size))
we can just create the indices, and then see m_IndexBuffer.reset(IndexBuffer::Create(indices, size))
并且那就是我们需要的，size就是sizeof(indices)，实际上这就是不错的关键点了
and that's all we need, and size is just sizeof indices, now actually this is a good point
对吧，那么关键是我们到底需要大小，还是应该需要数量
right, so the point is do we actually need size here, or should we rather have a count
原因是你们指定了uint32_t，就知道它们的大小，所以为什么不直接计数呢
the reason is that you're specifying uint32_t indices they, you know the size of them, anyway, so why not just have a count
我们在IndexBuffer中还有个，就是count，对吧，那么就是virtual uint32_t GetCount()
and the other thing that we actually do need in IndexBuffer, which I have neglected is the count, right, so virtual uint32_t GetCount()
对吧，然后这个就会告诉我们，在IndexBuffer中，实际上有多少个索引
and right, and then this will just tell us how many indices are actually in IndexBuffer
对渲染也很重要，因为我们想要普遍渲染所有的
which is important for rendering, since we want to commonly render all of them
那么这儿就会有virtual GetCount，返回m_Count，然后就是属性，uint32_t m_Count
so we'll have virtual GetCount here, which will return a count, m_Count, and then uint32_t m_Count
然后在这儿，当接收count时，设置count，就能做这个，然后这就是count*sizeof(uint32_t)
right, and then over here, when we take in the count, we'll set count, so that we can do this, and then this becomes count*sizeof(uint32_t)
好了，那么那就是我区分接收字节和非字节的方法
okay, so that's how I like to differentiate between what is in bytes and what is not in bytes
对吧，如果是count，那么就不是通过字节，它就是元素，这就意味着你们需要乘以大小
right, if it's count, then it's not in bytes, it's in elements, which means that you need to multiply by the size
如果它是size，就是通过字节传入，我们继续，很棒，那么现在返回Application
if it's size, it's in bytes, okay, there we go, wonderful, so now back inside our Application
我们创建了这个，在这个例子中我们没有indices，我们只有sizeof(indices)
we create this, we create these, and we instead of having indices in this case, we just have the sizeof(indices)
我们只有3个，因为这里有3个索引，看，我的意思是，如果你们想让它自动计算
we just have 3, because there's 3 indices in here, yeah look, I mean if you wanted this to be automated
你们就可以用sizeof，因为我知道有些人他们总是想用uint32_t，就像那样
you could just do sizeof, because I know some people gonna comply they always do uint32_t right like that
我在这里应该用什么，好了，然后那会给你们实际的数量
just what I should use here, alright, and then that will give you the actual a count
如果你们真的想那样做，这个会保持不变，然后我的意思是我们可能需要在某个点绑定它
if you really want to do it that way, this will keep the same, and then I mean we probably need to bind it at some point
如果我现在运行这个，可能不会得到一个三角形，因为这有点可疑
if I run this right now, probably won't give us a triangle, because this is a bit suspicious
不幸的是，我用完OpenGL已经有一段时间了，但我们会看到我们会得到什么
and unfortunately has been a while since I've used up in OpenGL, but we will see what we get here if anything
好吧，我们什么都没得到，我们得到了驱动内部的甭哭哦，是的，可能什么都没有绑定
okay, so we get nothing, and we get a crash in fact inside the driver, yeah probably nothing's bound
我的意思是试图在这绘制元素，我打赌没有什么可以绘制的，所以需要做的就使用
I mean we're trying to draw elements here, I bet we've got nothing to draw, so the other thing we need to do is actually use out
这里不是只有3个硬编码，我们应该得到IndexBuffer，并实际得到数量
instead of just having 3 hard-code here, we should get our IndexBuffer, and actually get the count
那就是我把它放在这里的原因，那么就来修改一下缓冲区，因为很明显我没有想象的那么好
that's why I wanted it here, okay, so let's fix up our buffers, because clearly I am not as good as I thought
我们需要绑定缓冲区，这意味着为什么要用create，为什么要用gen，在缓冲纹理是一样的
we need to bind our buffer, which I guess means that why to use create, why to use gen, they're the same in terms of buffers fleck textures
实际上你们马上就会指定目标，我可能觉得这里也会是一样的
you actually specify the target immediately, I kind of maybe thought that it would be like the same here
但我认为不是，对吧，那么这就是个IndexBuffer，OpenGL是不一致的，尽管代价是一致的
but I guess not, right, so this is the one IndexBuffer, so you know OpenGL have been inconsistent, even though price to be consistent
创建的原因只是为了匹配着色器，它有glCreateShaders，CreateShader和glCreateProgram
and the reason they have created now is just to match the shader api, which has glCreateShaders, you know CreateShader and glCreateProgram
但不管如何，我想我们会看到，所以那就是为什么你们应该使用create而不是gen
but anyway, I guess we'll see, so that's why you should still use creat instead of just gen
因为那样的话，接口是一致或者说OpenGL接口是一致的，让我们运行它，看看会发生什么
because that way your api is kind of consistent or rather your OpenGL api is consistent, let's run that and see what happens
既然我们已经有了边界，也让它有了边界，它现在应该在顶点上，一切都很好
and since we've bounded and left it bound, it should be in the vertex right now, and everything should be great
正如你们所看到的，希望这个能让你们对我在视频开始时所讲的内容有所了解
and as you can see it is, so hopefully that shed some light as to all the blabbing I did in the beginning of the video
比如你们知道的，你们必须这么做，必须创建这些类
where I was like you know, you have to do this, you have to create all these classes
现在我们已经完成了，你们可以看到我们在这里有基类，它们只是没有数据的接口
now we've done that, you can see we have the base classes here, which are just interfaces with no data at all
然后在运行时，我们选择返回一个特定渲染接口的特定实例，希望你们喜欢这期视频
and then at runtime, we make the choice to actually return a specific instance of a specific rendering api, hope you guys enjoyed this video
如果你们喜欢的话，就为它点赞吧，你们也可以访问patreon.com/thecherno来支持本系列
if you did, you can hit that like button, you can also help support the series by going to patreon.com/thecherno
非常感谢你们的支持，那也是本系列得以维持的动力
your support is greatly appreciated, and it is what keeps this series going
所以非常感谢所有帮助支持这个系列的朋友，让我知道你们对这种设计的看法吧
so huge thank you to everyone who helps support the series, let me know what you think of this kind of design
如果看到了其他你们认为更好的设计，请告诉我，这是我已经用了很多年的一个设计
let me know if you've seen other designs that you think are better, this is the one that I've kind of been using for years
说实话，这是我最喜欢的，因为所有的决定都是在运行时做出的，而且是在性能方面
and to be honest, it's my favorite, because all the decisions are made at runtime, and in terms of performance
我不知道，有些人可能会说
like I don't know, some people out there might be nipicking being like
但每次都是虚拟调度，没关系，老实说，真的没有太大关系
but it's a virtual dispatch every time, it doesn't matter, like it it honestly, doesn't matter
我曾经围绕着这种东西进行过基准测试，但我从未在编写游戏或引擎时遇到过这种情况
I've done benchmarks around this kind of stuff, I have never been in this situation, where I've written a game or an engine
并且我也一直在想，我希望我有非虚函数调用会有的额外性能
and I've been like man, you know, I wish I had the extra performance that having non virtual function calls would have had
我不是说这种情况不存在，我是说根据我的经验
I mean not saying that that scenario doesn't exist, I'm saying in my experience
对于我正在做的，对于我以后会用Hazel做的，这将是个非常高的性能，要求很高
and for what I'm doing, and for what I'm trying to do with Hazel which is going to be a very high performance, like quite demanding
视觉上，你们知道视觉上要求很高的引擎，对吧，这类东西肯定不会有什么影响
and visually you know visually demanding kind of engine, right, this kind of stuff definitely is not going to matter
如果你们正在构建一个非常小的引擎，比如嵌入式系统上的像素图像，也许这些会很重要
if you're making some really small engine for like pixel graphics on like an embedded system, yeah maybe this stuff would matter
但它不是这样的，在作业中，看看你们能不能创建Shader接口，因为现在我只有Shader
but it doesn't for something like this, for homework, see if you can create the shader api like this, because right now I've just got shader
我已经有了这个OpenGL函数的着色器类，而这个Buffer.cpp与OpenGL完全没有关系
I've got the shader class for this actually just OpenGL functions, whereas this Buffer.cpp file has no relation to OpenGL at all
对吧，我们包含了OpenGLBuffer，但那是，只有当我们在支持它的平台上
right, we include OpenGLBuffer, but that's again, only if we're on the platform that supports it
还有，你们知道的，我们没有包含glad之类的库，顺便说一下，OpenGLBuffer也没有
and also you know, we're not including glad or anything like that, and neither is OpenGLBuffer by the way
如果看看OpenGL，如果快速看下Buffer类，没有包含glad，对吧，但是cpp文件包含了
if you look at OpenGL, if we just quickly look at the Buffer class, this doesn't include glad, right, the cpp file does
所以实际上我们从没有把glad包含到通用Buffer类，不应该那样做，对吧，DirectX也一样
so we're never actually including glad into our generic buffer class and we shouldn't, right, same with kind of DirectX
你们通常不希望DirectX那样做，因为你们只会在Windows上构建它
you usually don't want to do that with DirectX is probably okay, because you'll be only building that on Windows
但对于这样的东西，我们甚至不需要，如果你们能避免它，肯定就避免了，然后是另一个
but for something like this, we don't even need to, and if you can avoid it, you definitely should, and then the other one
你们可以尝试封装VertexArray，看看能否让Application类完全通用
you can have a go with is VertexArray, and just see if you can make that application class completely kind of generic
不管怎样，我希望你们喜欢这期很长的视频，我已经在这里坐了差不多一个小时了
anyway, I hope you guys enjoyed this very long episode, been sitting here for like an hour almost
下次我想我们会更多地控制Renderer类或者
next time I think we're gonna either take more control with the renderer class or
我还想说说VertexArray以及如何适配，以及如何抽象，也许还有BufferLayout
I really want to also talk about VertexArray and how they fit in, and how we can abstract that and maybe the BufferLayout as well
但是请告诉我你们想看什么，我们下次见，再见
but yeah let me know what you want to see, and I'll see you guys next time, goodbye